<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The difference about church government ended: by taking away the distinction of government into ecclesiasticall and civill: and proving the government of the civill magistrate onely sufficient in a Christian kingdom. / Written by one that by making peace, prefers to be called a blessed childe of God, before preeminence in this world. J.M. D. D. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89003</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E339_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200855</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861481</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861481</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113618</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89003)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113618)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E339[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The difference about church government ended: by taking away the distinction of government into ecclesiasticall and civill: and proving the government of the civill magistrate onely sufficient in a Christian kingdom. / Written by one that by making peace, prefers to be called a blessed childe of God, before preeminence in this world. J.M. D. D. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 14, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.L. for William Leake, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Crowne in Fleetstreet between the two Temple gates.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>J.M. = Jasper Mayne.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 30th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113618:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113618:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
DIFFERENCE
ABOVT
CHURCH
GOVERNMENT
<hi>ENDED:</hi>
By taking away the Diſtinction of
Government into Eccleſiaſticall and Civill: and
proving the Government of the Civill
Magiſtrate onely ſufficient in a
Chriſtian Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Written by one that by making peace, prefers to be called a
bleſſed childe of God, before preiminence in this world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>J. M.</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed according to Order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi>
Printed, by <hi>R. L.</hi> for <hi>William Leake,</hi> and are to be
ſold at his ſhop at the ſigne of the Crowne in <hi>Fleet ſtreet</hi>
between the two Temple gates. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113618:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113618:2"/>
            <head>To the High and Honourable Court
of PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving penned my Meditations
about Church Government, I
had ſome thoughts to commend
them (right Chriſtian and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
Senate) to your conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
and protection. But being
conſcious to my ſelf of my own
weakneſſe, I was ſometime in
ſuſpence, as thinking it too high
preſumption for me ſo to do. But
for ſo much as that which I have here written, is, as I am
perſwaded the Truth of God, and tends to the entituling of
you to that power which of right belongs unto you, as I doubt
not, but yee out of your own profound wiſdome are inclinable
to think and hold: (whereby if yee do not ſpeedily ſet this
power aworke, Diviſions and Errours and Contentions are
likely to increaſe amongst us more and more, and ſo for want
of a timely proviſion made, Iniquity and Hereſie to abound
<pb facs="tcp:113618:3"/>
more, to the blemiſhing of our Church and Gods high diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour)
I have made bold, as a feeling member of Chriſts my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall
body, to preſent it to your honourable view. And if upon
peruſall yee ſhall think it to be the Truth, I beſeech you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace
it, and knowing what the power is, which in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Kingdome ought to beare ſway both in Church and
Common-wealth, for the curbing and puniſhing of all evill
doers, delay not to ſet it up. And <hi>eadem opera,</hi> quell the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion
ſo dangerous, which ariſeth from the groundleſſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction,
as I conceive, betwixt Government Civill and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
amongst us, and let the ſword of the Magiſtrate
be regularly ſharpned against thoſe new upſtart blaſphemous
Seducers, upon whom it ſhall appeare that the ſword of the
ſpirit can do no good, and in this ſo neceſſary a worke the God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
of Heaven direct and bleſſe your pious endevours, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
already he hath done great and mighty acts by you for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
of the Church and Commonwealth, ſo he may make you inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments 
of this good to his Church alſo. And ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
ving pardon for my preſumption, and that it may be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
to a good deſire, I rest ready whether approved or reproved, to
ſubmit to your cenſures.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113618:3"/>
            <head>The difference about Church-Government
ended.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He great controverſie of theſe times being about
the government of the Church, whereby wee
may come into as great danger of cruel diſconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
when the preſent ſhall by Gods bleſſing be
ended, and diverſe Books being written, <hi>pro</hi>
and <hi>contra,</hi> by Presbyterians and Independants
here about, whereby the difference is not likely
to be compoſed, but increaſed more and more<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Give me leave, though
the leaſt and unworthieſt of them all, in briefe to declare what I
conceive, and I thinke can ſolidly prove to be the onely true and
right way wherein we ought to goe. And that God whom I have
ſought unto for light herein, make my pure endeavours ſuccesfull,
that this way being diſcovered, we may all with one conſent walke
and perſevere in the ſame: and this is not the way by me firſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,
but being ſtood for by ſome others before, that which upo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſerious ſtudy and conſideration I am confirmed in more and more.
And it is that in a Chriſtian Kingdom the deſtinction betwixt Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall
and Secular power and rule in reſpect of the exteriour
exerciſe, by cenſuring and puniſhing offenders ceaſeth, all this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
being in the ſame perſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the higher powers, who are
Gods Vicegerents upon earth, to mannage all Rule and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
over all cauſes and perſons under their Dominion, whether
Secular or Eccleſiaſticall, and that Eccleſiaſticall perſons ought not
to have any ſhare or part in this power, but onely to diſpenſe the
myſteries of ſalvation, the Word and Sacraments, to put up the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions
of the congregation in publike, or of any particulars, as need
ſhall require, to ordaine new Presbyters, and to joyne man and
woman in marriage and in caſe of variance in opinion ariſing in
the Church to have the chiefe ſtroke in determining the truth in a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113618:4"/>
Councel, and the determination by them ſo made all ought, ſo
far as conſcience can poſſibly give leave, to ſtand to, of what eſtate
or degree ſoever they be, and to be ſubject and obedient to them,
or anyone of them in their ordinary adminiſtring of the Word,
the higher powers compelling their Subjects in all lawf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ways by
penalties, who will not otherwiſe, to obey and receive their whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
Doctrine in all things.</p>
            <p>For proof of all this, and firſt, that all power in a Chriſtian
Kingdom is in the ſame perſons, the higher powers, See <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1.
<hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> and as <hi>Bernard</hi> hath
it to Pope <hi>Engenius, Si omnis anima, etiam veſtra,</hi> here by higher
Powers are meant the civill Magiſtracie, as 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. is fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
explained where it is ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id, <hi>Obey every humane Ordinance for
the Lords ſake, whether the King as ſupreme, or thoſe that are ſet in
authority under him.</hi> Wherefore all power is primitively in the
King, where the Countrey is under a King, and derivatively inſuch
as have commiſſion from him, and theſe are only Secular men, not
Eccleſiaſticks, according to that of the Apoſtle, <hi>If yee have judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
in things pertaining to this life, ſet up them that are leaſt eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
in the Church, 1 Cor.</hi> 6. 4. That is, ſome common Chriſtians,
no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters of the Goſpel. And wherein the Magiſtrates pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
is, he ſheweth ſaying, <hi>He beareth not the Sword in vain,</hi> but <hi>for
the puniſhment of evill doers.</hi> From hence I argue thus.</p>
            <p>They onely ought to rule and govern by cenſures and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
that have this power given them of God:<note place="margin">Arg. 1.</note> but the civill
Magiſtrates onely have this power given them of God, <hi>ergo,</hi> they
onely ought to rule this way. The <hi>Major</hi> here cannot be doubted
of, becauſe all power is of God: Nor the <hi>Minor,</hi> becauſe it is the
expreſſe aſſertion of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>Again,<note place="margin">Arg. 2.</note> that Government only ought to be in a Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
which is neceſſary for the welbeing thereof, and any other is
ſuperfluous: but the government of the Civill Magiſtrate here is
only neceſſary, <hi>Ergo,</hi> none elſe ought to be. Here the <hi>Minor</hi> only
can be doubted (for <hi>fruſtra fit per plura<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quod poteſt fieri per pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciora</hi>)
but the truth hereof will appeare if we conſider, that there
is no ſin or errour in any ſort of men, but the ſword of the Civill
Magiſtrate cuts it down ſo ſoon as he hath notice thereof. Againſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113618:4"/>
murther, adultery and perjury. Magiſtrates even in Heathen Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
have bin from time to time very ſevere, as it is neceſſary they
ſhould, And againſt Witches, Idolaters, Drunkards, Theives,
common Swearers and Sabbath-breakers, the ſword is ſharpned in
this land, &amp; againſt Cheators, Forgeries and all other notoriotyes,
yea, and againſt Blaſphemers, &amp; Sorcerers, to Lyers, and thoſe that
believing them make diſturbance of the peace of the Kingdom, and
where the Laws are not ſufficiently penall, the penalties may be
aggravated. Our Laws alſo have provided, that perſons ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
in their lives living in variance and hatred, rayling and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
and not reconciled ſhould be kept from the holy Communion,
and now by Ordinance of Parliament it is provided, that igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
perſons ſhal be likewiſe hereby ſuſpended here from. And what
then remayns, for which there is need for any other power to
come in for, the well governing of the Church of Chriſt amongſt
us, but only to authorize Miniſters, to whom it properly belongeth
to try and find out, and ſuſpend the ignorant, ſome ſhort Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme
being firſt compiled of the Principles neceſſary by every
Chriſtian to be know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, beyond the bounds whereof no Miniſter
may go in his examinations, or having tryed admit of any through
partiality, that ſhall come ſhort of this knowledge, and in his try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
putting difference betwixt the ancient and the yonger, as Saint
<hi>Paul</hi> directeth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 1. dealing with them as fathers with theſe,
as brethren. And if the Miniſter through envy, pride, or enmity
ſhall proceed otherwiſe with any, then is preſcribed, hee may be
made lyable to give account thereof to the Magiſtrate; and if he be
found guilty, to puniſhment therefore, but if not, the party com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playning
to be ſoundly puniſht for his falſe accuſation. As for ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous
livers, let ſuch officers, as the Magiſtrate ſhall thinke fit, be
appointed in every Pariſh, but let them be of the moſt religious and
conſcionable, who may be tyed by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to preſent them unto him,
and as he ſhall find cauſe, let him direct his precept to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
to ſuſpend him, till he be reformed. If Officers ſo appointed be
negligent, let it be commended to the care of any in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotion,
who have the ſpirit of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in them, to complain of them
to the Magiſtrate, that upon proof he may be ſoundly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for his
negligence in a matter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>: of ſo great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:113618:5"/>
If none,<note place="margin">Arg. 3.</note> but Magiſtrates be capable of rule and dominion in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
of cenſures and puniſhments, then they only ought to have
the rule: but none elſe are capable hereof, <hi>Ergo,</hi> none elſe ought to
have this rule. The <hi>Minor</hi> which only can be doubted of is thus
proved. The Miniſter of the Goſpell is not capable of it <hi>Ergo,</hi> none
elſe. That he is not, appears, becauſe Chriſt oppoſeth the order of
Preachers to Rulers, ſaying, <hi>The Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe
dominion over them, but it ſhall not be ſo with you, Matth.</hi> 20. 25.
that is, ye ſhal not rule over your brethren, and the moſt faithfull A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle
<hi>Peter</hi> exhorting Presbyters to feed the flocke of Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to them, when hee comes to ſpeake of ruling, doth it with
this negative <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>not ruling over them, 1 Pet.</hi> 5. 1.</p>
            <p>If it be here objected,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> Elders are deſcribed by ruling, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.
17. <hi>The Elders that rule well, are worthy of double honour, Heb.</hi> 13.
7. 17, 24. they are three times likewiſe deſcribed, and ſuch other
additions made, as that it cannot be underſtood of any other Elders,
but Preachers, as namely, <hi>Verſe 7. that have the rule over you, who
have ſpoken unto you the Word of God. Verſe 17. that rule over you,
for they watch for your ſouls.</hi> Therefore any Presbyter, <hi>quatenus</hi> a
Presbyter preaching the Word of God, and a Watchman over
ſouls is and ought to be a Ruler, and have power to cenſure.</p>
            <p>I anſwer that the words rendred by ruling are in two of theſe
places <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> ſignifieth not Rulers, but leaders, but becauſe lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,
as Captains, are Rulers, it is rendred Rulers, though all lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
or guides in a way be not Rulers in the ſenſe here ſpoken of.
In the third place <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth alſo ſuch as goe before, not
properly Rulers or Governours, therefore from hence nothing can
be evinced to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>If it be further objected,<note place="margin">Ob.</note> the Keys are given to <hi>Peter,</hi> and by
Keys according to the Scripture phraſe government is always un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood,
as <hi>Eſay 22. 22. The key of the houſe of David I will lay
upon his ſhoulder, and he ſhall open and none ſhall ſhut,</hi> compared
with <hi>Chap. 9. 6. The government ſhall be upon his ſhoulder, Revel.</hi> 3.
7. <hi>He that hath the key of David.</hi> Here by the key of <hi>David</hi> is
plainly ſet forth ſovereigne power in all things, therefore are the
keys of the Kingdome of Heaven given to <hi>Peter, Matth.</hi> 16. the
power of governing in things partayning to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113618:5"/>
that is, the Church, and what power was here given to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi>
is ſhowed to be given to all the Apoſtles, <hi>Matth. 18. 18. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever
ye bind upon earth ſhall be bound in heaven &amp;c:</hi> becauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the power of the keys is ſhewed to lye by the words noted in
the place before named, <hi>Whatſoever thou bindeſt upon earth, ſhall
be bound in heaven,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> 20. 23. the ſame power is given to all
the Apoſtles in words to the ſame effect, <hi>Whoſe ſins you remit they
are remitted, &amp;c:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accordingly exerciſed this power,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. by delivering <hi>Hymenens</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> to Satan, &amp;
touching the inceſtuous perſon as <hi>Corinth,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I have judged,
to deliver him to Satan, 1 Cor.</hi> 5. 3. but this he could not have done,
unleſſe he had had ſuch power. And as having power to commit
the like to other Preachers, hee gave <hi>Timothy</hi> a charge over the
Church at <hi>Epheſus, 1 Tim.</hi> 1. 1. 18. and by vertue hereof he was to
charge ſome not to preach any other doctrine, Implying a ruling
power committed unto him, and to <hi>Titus</hi> to order things in <hi>Creet,
Titus</hi> 1. 5. and <hi>Timothy</hi> is bidden to receive none accuſation againſt
an Elder under two or three witneſſes, <hi>Chap.</hi> 5 19. And what is he
that orders things in the Church, but a Ruler, or he before whom
accuſations are brought.</p>
            <p>To all this I anſwer, that <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sol.</note> and the reſt of the Apoſtles for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gave
ſins, and looſed by preaching ſalvation to the faithfull and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentant
and retained ſins, and damn'd by preaching damnation
to the impenitent, and <hi>Paul</hi> accurſeth thoſe that teach any other
Doctrine, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1. Yea, and I doubt not, but by vertue of that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,
they and other Preachers their ſucceſſors, during the time
that the Chriſtian Religion was imbraced but by ſome, and thoſe,
of the meane: ſort, the greateſt, as Emperours, Kings, and Princes
withſtanding it, had a ruling power by excommunications and
other cenſures ſpirituall to deter the wicked amongſt them, and
Hereticks and Schiſmaticks, and to make them aſhamed that they
might be brought to repentance, and to releaſe them again. But it
doth not hence follow that in a Chriſtian Kingdom, where there is a
ſword ſufficiently ſharpned againſt all notorious wickedneſſes in
people and in Miniſters, yea, and Magiſtrates alſo doing unjuſtly,
that this cenſuring power of binding and looſing in particular
Courts of Juſtice ſhould bee continued for the reaſon before going.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113618:6"/>
And thus the objection made from the power given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and
<hi>Titus</hi> is anſwered alſo, it was but <hi>pro tempore,</hi> when Kings ſhould
come on to be Chriſtians, the faithfull as well as others being then
ſubjected to this civill coercive power, in all things as they were
by <hi>Titus</hi> his teaching to be prepared, <hi>Tit. 3. 1. Put them in
minde to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, and to obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi>
and it is reckoned up as one of the black brands of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate
Chriſtians, <hi>Jude ver. 8. To deſpiſe Dominions, and to ſpeake
evill of dignities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it will not be granted,<note place="margin">Arg. 3.</note> that if Preachers be not capable of
this rule, that none elſe but Magiſtrates are<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for there be other
governments diſtinct from Paſtors and Teachers in the Church,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. and <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8. the ſame is plainly intimated, when
after theſe charges, <hi>Let him that miniſtreth tend upon his miniſtring,
and he that teacheth on teaching, &amp;c.</hi> it is added, <hi>hee that ruleth
with diligence,</hi> and agreeably to theſe places 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. It is ſaid,
<hi>The Elder that rules well is worthie of double honour,</hi> therefore
there ought to be other Rulers in the Church beſides the Magiſtrate,
to whom it properly belongs to cenſure in things Eccleſiaſticall.
I anſwer, it is to be noted that the Ruler ſpoken of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 8.
and likewiſe the Governments. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 28. are put after not
onely Paſtors and Teachers but Helpes, ſet forth by <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
that is Deacons alſo, as being the loweſt order in the Church,
whereby is plainly intimated, that they had no power of cenſuring,
for then they ſhould as ſuperiours have been placed before them,
over whom they had power, or amongſt whom they had the chiefe
power. 2. In two of theſe places the ſame word is uſed, which
hath been already ſhewed, to ſignifie nothing but leaders, or men
ſet over others or goers before, and therefore if there be ſome in
each congregation ſet onely over the manners of men: to obſerve
the irregular, and to admoniſh them, and if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
wil not reform, to preſent them to the Magiſtrate, ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as the
Apoſtle means are not wanting in the Church, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſhal we ſay
to the governments ſpoken of in the third place, doth not this word
imply a power to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it doth, for Government is neceſſary
to the well being of the Church of God<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but becauſe he ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, not
Governours, but Governments, the Office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113618:6"/>
the notorieties of men are brought to light that they might have
condigne cenſure and puniſhment may well be underſtood by a
Synechdoche, becauſe the Governours in whom the power is,
are holpen in their ruling by them. For it is not credible either
that any of the common people ſhould have power over their
Teachers, or that by governments any other are ment, then ſuch as
are otherwiſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as theſe Officers may well be,
and yet not in ſo high a degree as they that preach the Word of
God, for which they are ſet ſo low under them. The Government
then goes right, according to the meaning of the Apoſtle, when
the higher powers having cenſured they ſee to the execution, as
are vigilant to examine privately, and to preſent the ſcandalous, and
in the primitive times when they did thus officiate to the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie,
conſiſting of grave and learned teachers. If it ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe,
none, it is to be feared, will be found fit in diverſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,
for ſuch authority, either for want of knowledge or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blameableneſſe
of life. 2 If any be in theſe reſpects, yet not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<hi>homines plebes,</hi> and ſo ſubject to contempt, amongſt their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
who would never ſtoop but to their ſuperiours in outward
reſpects, to be ruled by them. 3 If they would, yet ſuch indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
ſhould hereby be offered to Teachers, as were intollerable, and
diſcouraging to ſome, either to enter the Miniſtry, or to continue
in it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Arg. 4.</note> no ſuch government ought to be in a Chriſtian King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
but what hath been by Gods own direction or allowance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
his ancient people, the Iſraelites: but there was never any
government Eccleſiaſticall diſtinct from the Civill. <hi>Ergo,</hi> none
ſuch ought now to be in a Chriſtian Kingdome. For the <hi>Major</hi> it
appears to be true, becauſe neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles taught
any thing, but what there was ground for in the Law and the
Prophets. <hi>Caeſar</hi> muſt have the things of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the Miniſter that
Preacheth the Goſpell muſt live upon the Goſpell, as they that
wayted upon the Altar, of the Altar. To preach and pray belongs
to his office, as to the Prieſts to teach and offer ſacrifices for the
people. And as none might preſume to doe this Prieſtly office, but
the Prieſt, ſo none may preach, unleſſe they be ſent; that is, be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained
according to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ection of Gods holy Word, that is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113618:7"/>
firſt proved, then having the impoſition of the hands of the
Presbytery, conſiſting, not of Laym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in part, but altogether of
Preachers, for as much as wee no where read of the impoſition of
hands by any other. For the <hi>Minor, Moſes</hi> was firſt the ſole Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,
and when this burthen was thought to be too great for him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,
ſeventy two more were joyned with him to help to beare it,
<hi>Numb.</hi> 11. being choſen by ſixes out of every Tribe, of which
Tribes <hi>Levi</hi> was counted none, there being twelve Tribes beſides
to make up this number. After this the Judge and the ſeventy two
ruled in all things. Light and direction to proceed according to
Gods will, they were indeed to ſeek of the high Prieſt and Prieſts,
<hi>whoſe lips muſt preſerve knowledge, and they muſt enquire the Law
at his mouth, Mal.</hi> 2. 7. So <hi>Joſhuaſh</hi> muſt ſeek to <hi>Eleazer</hi> the high
Prieſt, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27. 21. and in any difficult caſe they muſt come to
the Prieſts, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 9. but the Judge and the Counſell of ſeventy
two had all the power. Afterwards when Kings raigned in <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
King <hi>Solomon</hi> put <hi>Abiather</hi> the high Prieſt from his office, ſetting
up <hi>Zadoe,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> diſtinguiſhed the courſes of the Prieſts and
other Godly Kings from time to time ruled in things Eccleſiaſtical
and Prieſts never, till that after their return from the Babyloniſh
captivity, Princes failing in the time of <hi>Antiochus, Epiphanes,
Mattathias</hi> the Prieſt, and his ſonnes being neceſſitated to it took
the government upon them both in things ſecular and ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Matth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ob.</note> 18. 17. <hi>Tell it to the Churches,</hi> and why to the Church,
but becauſe it was his will that the Church ſhould have power of
cenſuring, and if ſo, then not the Magiſtrate alone.</p>
            <p>By the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> rendred Church,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> is not always underſtood
the Congregation of Chriſtians, but ſometime any aſſembly, as
<hi>Acts</hi> 19. 41. Here therefore may well be underſtood the judicatory,
that then was amongſt the Jews before ſpoken of which yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued,
and amongſt them when any ſhould afterwards be ſet up,
of what perſons ſoever it conſiſted, and not any whole congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
that were ſuch a government as was never heard of in thoſe
times, or the times preceding neither is it neceſſary that they ſhould
be Officers properly Eccleſiaſticall, but any of the more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
amongſt people who have alſo power in the Common-wealth,
may conſtitute this judicatory, but for the power of binding and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113618:7"/>
loſing ſpoken of <hi>Verſe</hi> 18. it belongs not to them, but to Preachers
for which he changeth the perſon, ſaying, <hi>What yee bind upon earth
ſhall be bound in Heaven,</hi> hereby giving them power <hi>pro tempore,</hi>
that the inordinate might be awed till that Magiſtrates being
converted they might be otherwiſe curbed. To cleere which the
more, take this for a paraphraſe. If thy brother ſin againſt thee
by doing thee any treſpaſſe or traducing thee, or detracting from
thee, or offering thee any violence, and neyther by private telling
him of it, nor by mediation of friends hee will be brought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
his fault, and ask thee forgiveneſſe, tell the Judges of it,
who have authority to proceed againſt offenders that they may, if
it be poſſible by threatning him with puniſhment cauſe him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
but if not ſo, give him over for an heathen incorrigible and
no true Chriſtian, and let the Miniſters of the Church exclude him
from the Sacrament or Communion of Chriſtians &amp; conſequently
from life, neyther let him contemne, becauſe they that exclude
him are but two or three d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſpicable Miniſters of the Goſpel, who
have none authority or power in this world. For whatſoever yee
thus proceeding binde ſhall be bound, &amp;c. Yea, if there be not
two but only one in that Church, for as it is here ſayd, <hi>Whatſoever
yee bind</hi> in the plurall number, ſo <hi>Matth.</hi> 16. It is ſayd, <hi>Whatſoever
thou bindeſt.</hi> And by vertue of this Commiſſion <hi>Paul</hi> alone delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> to Satan, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 20. If it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded,
ſhall he not be bound from comming to the Congregation
alſo? <hi>Anſ.</hi> By no means, becauſe even Heathens came into the
Congregations, as may be gathered, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2. and if not, how ſhould
they be converted? wherefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> excommunicating wholly our
of the Church for any ſin is lawfull.</p>
            <p>1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Object.</note> 5. <hi>Paul</hi> requires the <hi>Corinth:</hi> Church <hi>to put the inceſtuous
man from amongst them,</hi> which argues authority to cenſure in the
Church.</p>
            <p>I deny not,<note place="margin">Sol.</note> but in thoſe times, there being yet no Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy
it was neceſſary, that there ſhould be ſome authority in the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, who preached the word to ſentence groſſe offenders,
who would other wiſe have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to the greater blemiſhing
of Chriſtianity. But this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that it ought ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be in a
Chriſtian Kingdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> can be ſuffered,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113618:8"/>
although there be no Church Government to animadvert againſt
him.</p>
            <p>Having this proved, that the Government in all things in a
Chriſtian Kingdom is and ought to be in the Civill Magiſtrate, let
us now conſider the other part of my generall Propoſition concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
the Miniſters of the Goſpell. That to them it is committed to
Preach and Baptize, and adminiſter the Supper of the Lord is plain
from the laſt words of Chriſt, <hi>Go teach all Nations baptizing them,
&amp;c. Matth.</hi> 28. and from the charge at the Inſtitution of the Lords
Supper. <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> And they only may do theſe
things, in any other it is pride and preſumption highly diſpleaſing to
God to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as in <hi>Saul</hi> to ſacrifice &amp; in <hi>Uzziak</hi> to burn Incenſe.
2 That to them alſo it belongs to put up the Petitions of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation
&amp; of particular perſons in diſtreſſe, we may gather from Gods
Ordinance that the Prieſts ſhould offer Sacrifice for the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and for any perſon having treſpaſſed, but now troubled for it,
of the Prophets, praying alſo in the Congregation, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.
and for the ſick, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5. 16. Kings have ſometimes prayed publikely
alſo, though they might not Sacrifice, as <hi>Solomon</hi> at the Dedication
of the Temple, and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> when many kept the Paſſover, who
were not cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſed, piety putting them on to it, and no prohibition
lying againſt it. But theſe were rare and extraordinary acts and not
be ordinarily drawn into imitation, as neyther that of <hi>Phineas</hi> a
Prieſt killing <hi>Coſby</hi> and <hi>Zimri,</hi> and afterward going as a Captain
againſt the <hi>Midianites.</hi> For not <hi>Moſes</hi> but <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt bleſſe or
pray publikly for the Congregation, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 23. And when the
plague was in the Hoſt, he, not <hi>Moſes</hi> muſt go up with his Cenſor
by offering incenſe to ſtay it. 3 For ordayning Elders or Biſhops
it is committed to <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> not to others, who were not
Preachers, or Elders themſelves, and <hi>Acts 14. 23. Paul</hi> and <hi>Barna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi>
ordained Elders in every Church. 4 For joyning man and
wiſe together, becauſe it ought not to be without prayer, bleſſing
and inſtructing, and that in publike, who is ſo fit to doe it as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter.
5 For obedience and ſubmiſſion unto them, though they
have no power by cenſure in judiciary proceeding to compell, yet
conſiderig the command, obey them that go before you in doctrine,
and life, and are your Leaders, and ſubmit your ſelves to them, as to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113618:8"/>
them, <hi>that watch for your ſonis, Heb.</hi> 13. 17. There is no good
Chriſtian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of what eſtate or degree ſoever, but for conſcience
towards him that commands this, will readily do it. For when <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dekiah</hi>
and the Princes of <hi>Judah</hi> would not obey <hi>Jeremiah.</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to them in the name and word of the Lord, what grievous
things did they ſuffer by the <hi>Caldees.</hi> 6 For the Miniſters or
Presbyters power in Councel, to manage controverſies in point of
Religion, &amp; to determine, that which was done in the firſt famous
Councel at <hi>Jeruſalem, Act.</hi> 15. ſpeaks plainly, &amp; therefore it hath
been followed as a preſident in the pureſt times, by all the Chriſtian
World, and that not without good ſucceſſe in many ages, to the
ſuppreſſing of monſtrous errors, and to the keeping up of the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
of faith. Thus I have, by Gods aſſiſtance, made good my
whole propoſition, which if it might in all parts be ſubſcribed to,
Oh! what great good would enſue to us all thereby? The great
controverſie touching Church Government ſo greatly troubling
and diſturbing the whole Kingdom would be ſopi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
betwixt Presbyterians and Independants ended, the many
ſtrange and monſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ous errours lately ſprung up, extirpated, claſhing
and enterfeeing betwixt two ſorts of Governments removed, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
men and Hereticks, who feare not the word, nor regard Church
cenſures, terrified, and peace throughout the whole Kingdom
ſetled. Now that I may yet more effectually move the mindes of
all my brethren who ſhall read this, I ſhall add, that as it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
for the civill Magiſtrate to take all the gove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nment into his
hands, even in things Ecleſiaſticall, as hath been ſaid, ſo it is moſt
expedient for us of the Miniſtry that they ſhould ſo doe, becauſe
being exempt from this trouble, we ſhall be the more free to prayer,
reading, meditation, preaching, and other holy offices properly
belonging to our function, That thus we ought to bee, appears
from the reaſon given by the Apoſtles, why they would have Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons
choſen to be over matters concerning the poor, <hi>viz.</hi> that they
might wholy give themſelves to prayer, and the miniſtry of the
Word, <hi>Act.</hi> 6. 4. For if the preacher muſt not be troubled about
matters of charity, to gather and to diſtribute collections amongſt
the poor, but ſome others of the congregation muſt have this of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,
how much leſſe ought he to be troubled by keeping Cour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113618:9"/>
at ſet times, and hearing and cenſuring ſins complained of there,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 13, 15. he muſt give himſelfe wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to reading, prayer,
exhortation and Doctrine, and in ſo doing hee ſhall ſave himſelfe
and thoſe that heare him.</p>
            <p>2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We ſhall be leſſe liable to the emnity of the wicked, who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be without a grudge againſt ſuch as puniſh them, as experience
hath taught in ſome other Church, wherein a ruling power is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
to Miniſters amongſt others. It is true indeed, that a faithfull
Preacher cannot avoid the hatred of the wicked, for they hated
Chriſt aad therefore will hate them: yet becauſe they can leſſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re
to be cenſured by them, whom they know by birth to be mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
then themſelves, eſpecially ſome of them, it is more convenient
that for this they ſhould be dealt with by men of eminencie in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
reſpects, that their prejudice againſt the Preacher may be the
leſſe, and ſo he may be in more poſſibility, by his teaching, to doe
their ſouls good. And for the like reaſon, no godly man of mean
quality in any congregation can conveniently be ſet up as a Ruler
over others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe ſo he ſhall become more ſubject to conterupt
and deriſion, and be made leſſe able to doe good amongſt his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
in private by ſtirring them up to love and good works, as
hath been already ſaid.</p>
            <p>3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> We are Embaſſadours of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 20. and therefore
not to exerciſe power by cenſuring in anothers Kingdom, ſuch as
the world of the wicked is: for they are under the Prince of the
Ayre, and therefore by us to be dealt with, not by puniſhment, but
by entreaty.</p>
            <p>4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Preacher being but a man, and yeſterday as it were, but,
a Boy, and the contemptible ſon of a man of low degree, and every
Preacher not having grace, judgment &amp; gravity fit for government
if he be inveſted with power, is apt hereby to be puft up, and in u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
it, not to ſerve Chriſt, but his own luſts and paſſions, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
to avoid this inconvenience, it is better for us to be without
this power, then to have it, that we may be kept humble, and ſo the
more gracious, and have our Auditours the more ready to hearken
to us. For being in this ruling office, the beſt ſhall hardly eſcape the
imputation of pride and although it be falſly, yet the power of our
teaching will be much hereby weakned, ſith pride is contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113618:9"/>
both to God and man. And here do not, I beſeeth you, my
Brethren, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out upon me and ſay, I deal unnaturally thus to ſeek
to pull down, and bring under all my fellow ſervants, and to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
the honour of dominion from them to the Magiſtrate even in
things pertayning to their calling. For ye ſhall ſtill have the higheſt
honour in the world higher then Judges, for all men ſhall be judged
according to your Goſpel, then Nobles, for their greateſt honour
is to be ſent Embaſſadours by earthly Kings but yours that ye are
Embaſſadours of Chriſt, theirs that they may be the Kings Privy
Counſellors, yours, that God makes you of his counſell, for the
Lord will do nothing but he reveals it to his ſervants the Prophets,
and again theirs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they are Generals of Armies to ſubdue Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels,
and to quell Enemies, yours that ye have weapons and ſtrength
committed to you to overthrow ſtrong holds, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 4. and to
root out and deſtroy Kingdoms and Nations, that be rebellious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
God, <hi>Jer.</hi> 1. 10. Laſtly, higher then Kings, for their greateſt
honour is that they rule over the outward man, yours that ye rule
and have power in the conſcience in ſuch as have a conſcience,
theirs that they bear the ſecular ſword, yours that ye manage the
ſpirituall, which is ſharper then any two-edged ſword, theirs that
they can terrifie by threatning corporal death yours that ye threaten
eternall, and laſtly theirs that they are over all other men in things
pertaining to men, yours that ye are over all other men, &amp; them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
in things pertayning to God, and to their everlaſting welfare to
teach, guide and direct them, and to bleſſe them, whereby they
may be furthered thereunto, and if yet ye would have more, take
this as the greateſt perfection of bleſſedneſſe, that in the regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
ye ſhall ſit upon thrones, and ſo come to the honour of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and reigning with Chriſt for ever. And if this be your honour,
though no rulling power be given unto you here, complain not of
being trodden down, but rather joy, that the government ſhould
be in ſuch hands as in whoſe of right it ought to be, and it is moſt
expedient for you that it be, and help what ye are able to bring it
to this, as every one, that prefers the truth before his own advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
ought to do. And ye Magiſtrates and Rulers of the world
be entreated to uſe this your power aright, in Gods way to beat
down errours and notorious ſins in every place, and as the ſemina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113618:10"/>
of errours, private preachings by ſuch as intrude themſelves into
this office, beig never called thereunto, as was <hi>Aaron,</hi> &amp; to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
to learning &amp; piety, &amp; to conſtancy in the truth, as being ſet up
to rule in all things, not for your ſelves, but for God, who hath of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular
mercy thus highly honoured you. If any ſhalthink this to be
written for ſlattery &amp; not in ſyncerity, he ſhal do me great wrong,
who as God knows, have none other end, but to bring the truth,
of which I am perſwaded to light, as ſeeing none other way to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſe
the terrible tempeſt of contrary winds of doctrine, ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly
toſſing the ſhip of the Church, that it is ready otherwiſe to
ſink in this State, which God forbid and therefore make every Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
that ſhall read me, not an high-ſpirited <hi>Diotrephes</hi> who loveth
preeminence, but a lowly minded <hi>Apollo,</hi> who ſubmitted himſelf to
learne the truth more perfectly, even of <hi>Priſcilla</hi> and <hi>Aquila</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though
he were a man mighty in the Word, and they but Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers,
how-ever more verſed at that time then he in the doctrine
of the Goſpel. But if any one being unſatisfied with that which hath
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſayd ſhall have a mind to contend, let me intreat him not to do it
with words comming from a pen dipt in gall and vinegar, but with
ſolid Argument according to that of <hi>Auguſtine, Sacrae Scripturae
authoritate res cum re, cauſa cum causâ, ratio cum ratione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113618:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
